纽约
New York,
一座充满了万千故事的城市
the city of a million stories.
这些故事一半是真  至于另一半
Half of them are true. The other half?
只是尚未发生而已
Just haven't happened yet.
雕像  那个男人说道
Statues, the man said.
活过来的雕像在黑暗中潜行
Living statues that moved in the dark.
那么  你愿意接下这个案子吗  加纳先生
So, will you take the case, Mr. Garner?
好啊  为什么不接
Sure. Why not?
因为你不相信我
Because you don't believe me.
25块钱一天  花费报销
For $25 a day, plus expenses,
你想让我信什么我就信什么
I'll believe any damn thing you like.
但你还是不相信雕像会动
But you don't believe that statues can move.
而你说得也对  加纳先生
And you're right, Mr. Garner,
它们确实不能动
they can't.
雕像当然不能动
Of course they can't.
在你看着它们的时候
When you're looking.
晚安  格雷尔先生
Goodnight, Mr. Grayle.
格雷尔给我的地址在一处公寓街区
The address Grayle gave me was an apartment block
在炮台公园附近
near Battery Park.
他说那里就是雕像存在的地方
He said it where the statues lived.
我问他  为什么不自己去查看
I asked him why he didn't go look himself.
他没有回答
He didn't answer.
格雷尔是我知道的最可怕的人
Grayle was the scariest guy I knew.
如果有什么东西能吓到他
If something scared him,
我倒想跟这东西握握手
I kind of wanted to shake its hand.
冬季码头
有人吗
Hello?
Hello?!
如发生火灾  请勿使用电梯
什么
What the...?
S·加纳
有人吗
Hello?
有人在吗
Anyone home?
私家侦探  S·加纳
谁
Hello.
你是谁
Who are you?!
他们来抓你了
They're coming for you.
他们会送你回去
They're going to send you back.
谁来  回哪里
Who's coming? Back where?
过去
In time.
回到过去
Back in time.
我就是你
I'm you.
我  就是你
I'm...you.
濒死
我  濒死的侦探
在开玩笑吧
You got to be kidding me.
冬季码头
神秘博士  第七季第五集
天使占领曼哈顿
纽约城在我的窗外怒吼
New York growled at my window,
但我已经准备好了
but I was ready for it.
我的长筒袜整齐周正
My stocking seams were straight,
我的口红鲜艳动人
my lipstick was combat-ready,
而我挤出的事业线
and I was packing cleavage
能醉倒6米开外的公牛
that could fell an ox at 20 feet.
博士  你又来了
Doctor, you're doing it again.
纽约记录报
我在读书
I'm reading!
读出声了  能请你别出声吗
Out loud. Please, could you not?
你哪里不一样了  是不是
There's something different about you, isn't there?
什么书
What's the book?
《梅乐蒂·梅隆》
"Melody Malone."
她是个私家侦探
She's a private detective
在纽约老城干活
in old-town New York.
她心如坚冰  娇唇欲滴
She's got ice in her heart and a kiss on her lips
虽有脆弱的一面  却深深隐藏
and a vulnerable side she keeps well-hidden.
这么说你读过
Oh, you've read it.
不  是你读的  很大声
No, you read it. Aloud.
然后还说了句"哎呀妈呀"
And then went "Yowzah."
只有你才会这么迷书里的角色
You know, only you could fancy someone in a book.
我只是在看书  我喜欢这封面
I'm just reading. I just like the cover.
能让我看看封面吗
Can we see the cover?
不  不行  我忙着呢
No. No. I'm busy.
是你的头发
It's your hair.
是你的头发吗
Is it your hair?
闭嘴吧你  我戴眼镜了
Oh, shut up. It's the glasses.
我现在都得戴老花镜了
I'm wearing reading glasses now.
在我鼻子上  看见没  就在这里
On my nose. See? There you go.
我不喜欢这眼镜
I don't like them.
弄得你眼睛都起皱纹了
They make your eyes look all liney.
其实没有
No, actually.
抱歉  不是眼镜的错
Sorry. They're fine.
继续
Carry on.
好吧  我去再买些咖啡来
O-kay. I'm going to go and get us some more coffee.
谁还想喝咖啡  我也想要  我去买
Who wants more coffee? Me too! I'll go!
罗伊
Rory.
-我的眼角已经有皱纹了吗  -有
- Do I have noticeable lines on my eyes now? - Yes.
没有
No.
你看都没看
You didn't look.
我之前仔细看了  我没发现
I noticed them earlier. Didn't notice them.
我记得很清楚  我没发现皱纹
I specifically remember not noticing them.
你正在雷区跳舞  百夫长
You walk among fire pits, centurion.
我非得过去吗
Do I have to come over there?
你愿意的话就过来
You can, if you like.
好吧  我们要有伴了
Well, we have company.
我要请个保姆
I'll get a babysitter.
你们亲嘴的时候真是丢死人了
Do you know, it is so humiliating when you do that.
喝咖啡吗
Coffee?
喝咖啡吧
Coffee.
我能试试吗
Can I have a go?
别说  还真清楚多了
Actually, that is much better.
真是刺激
That is exciting.
给我念念
Read to me.
你不是不喜欢我读出声吗
I thought you didn't like my reading aloud.
闭上嘴  给我念个故事
Shut up and read me a story.
只要别又"哎呀妈呀"就行
Just don't go "Yowzah!"
你撕下来干什么
Why did you do that?
我总是把一本书的最后一页撕下来
Oh, I always rip out the last page of a book.
这样就不用结尾了
Then it doesn't have to end.
我讨厌结束
I hate endings.
我穿过街道
As I crossed the street,
看见这么一个瘦削男子  但他没有看见我
I saw the thin guy, but he didn't see me.
看来就是这么开始的
I guess that's how it began.
我跟着他走过了两个多街区
I followed the skinny guy for two more blocks
然后他转过身来
before he turned
而我想知道他到底为什么来这里
and I could ask exactly what he was doing here.
他似乎有些害怕
He looked a little scared,
所以我拿出最甜美的微笑和我湛蓝的双眼
so I gave him my best smile and my bluest eyes.
当心  别又"哎呀妈呀"出声了
And beware of the "Yowzah."
这个时候千万别哎呀妈呀
Do not, at this point, yowz.
博士  那个瘦子说什么了
Doctor? What did the skinny guy say?
他说
He said,
"我只是去买咖啡
"I just went to get coffees
"给博士和艾米
"For the Doctor and Amy.
梅乐蒂·梅隆
你好啊  瑞雯"
Hello, River."
你好啊  老爸
Hello, Dad.
我在哪
Where am I?
我怎么到这里来了
How the hell did I get here?
我完全不知道
I haven't the faintest idea.
但你最好把手举起来
But you'll probably want to put your hands up.
梅乐蒂·梅隆
Melody Malone?
你就是书里那个梅乐蒂
You're Melody?!
上车
Get in.
瑞雯怎么到书里去了
What's River doing in a book?
罗伊又怎么到书里去了
What's Rory doing in a book?
他去买咖啡了  认真听着
He went to get coffee. Pay attention.
他去买了趟咖啡  然后买到书里去了
He went to get coffee and turned up in a book.
这是什么原理
How does that work?
我不知道  我们可是在纽约
I don't know! We're in New York!
到底是怎么回事
What is going on?
-你从哪买的这本书  -就在我上衣的口袋里
- Where did you get this book? - It was in my jacket.
怎么进到你的口袋的
How did it get there?
这个那个又是怎么去这去那的  我都懒得问
How does anything get there? I've given up asking.
日期  日期  书里写到日期了吗
Date. Date. Does she mention a date?
这是什么时候的事
When is this happening?
好  你稍等
Yes, hang on.
1938年4月3日
April 3, 1938.
你显然不是坐塔迪斯来的
You didn't come here in the TARDIS, obviously.
怎么说
Why?
你不可能是
You couldn't have.
不可能是
Couldn't have?
她什么意思  不可能是
What does she mean, "Couldn't have"?
这座城市到处都是时空扭曲
This city's full of time distortions.
塔迪斯根本无法在这里降落
Be impossible to land the TARDIS here.
就好像在暴风雪中降落飞机
Like trying to land a plane in a blizzard.
就连我也做不到
Even I couldn't do it.
就连谁也做不到
Even who couldn't do it?!
你们两个少吵架
Don't you two fall out.
她只是在书里说说
She's only in a book.
1938年  简单得很
1938. Easy one.
警报  检测到时空扭曲
无信号
那是什么
What was that?
1938年
1938.
我们被弹出来了
We just bounced off it.
你又是怎么到这里来的
Well, how did you get here?
时空调制器  没塔迪斯那么大块头
Vortex Manipulator. Less bulky than a TARDIS.
就像穿行于车流间的摩托车
A motorbike through traffic.
你呢
You?
我
I'm...
不确定
not sure.
哭泣天使
The weeping Angels.
说得通
It makes sense.
说什么
It makes what?
罗伊就是遭遇了这个  天使就是干这个的
That's what happened to Rory. That's what the Angels do.
这是他们最喜欢的攻击方式
It's their preferred form of attack.
他们把你扔到过去的时间
They zap you back in time,
让你活到自然死亡
let you live to death.
可是我们有时间机器
Well, we've got a time machine.
我们可以直接去救他
We can just go and get him.
我们试过了  请你留意一下
Well, tried that, if you've noticed,
而我们又回到了起点  2012年
and we are back where we started, in 2012!
我们的起点不在墓园
We didn't start in a graveyard.
我们来这里干什么
What are we doing here?
不知道  大概是随机链接过来了
Don't know. Probably causally linked, somehow.
无所谓了
Doesn't matter.
抽烟机开启
Extractor fans on!
我们总得想办法过去
Well, we're going to get there, somehow.
剩下的章节里有我们
We're in the rest of the book.
什么里
In what?
第43页  你要弄断什么东西
Page 43. You're going to break something.
我弄什么
I'm what?
"你为什么非要弄断我的"
"Why do you have to break mine?"
我问博士  他皱起眉头说道
I asked the Doctor. He frowned and said,
"因为艾米在书里看到过
"Because Amy read it in a book
而现在我没有选择"
and, now, I have no choice."
停下  不  别读了  剩下的你不能读了
Stop! No! No! Stop! You can't read ahead.
千万不能  可不能这么做
You mustn't and... and you can't do that.
但我们已经在看了
But we've already been reading it.
但那只是正在发生的事情
Just the stuff that's happening now,
和我们同时的  我们只能看这么远
in parallel with us. That's as far as we go.
但这有助于我们找到罗伊
It could help us find Rory.
万一你读到后面发现罗伊死了呢
And if you read ahead and find that Rory dies?
这可不是普通的未来  艾米  这是我们的
This isn't any old future, Amy, it's ours.
一旦我们知道将要发生什么  就注定了
Once we know what's coming, it's fixed.
我要弄断什么东西
I'm going to break something
只因为你告诉我  我将要弄断什么东西
because you told me that I'm going to do it.
于是我没有选择
No choice now.
但时间可以改写
Time can be rewritten.
你读过之后就不能了
Not once you've read it.
一旦我们知道将要发生什么
Once we know it's coming,
就变成石碑上的字  改不了了
it's written in stone.
深切缅怀  罗伊·亚瑟·威廉姆斯
是秦朝早期的文物
Ah, early Chin Dynasty, I'd say.
正确
Correct.
这么说你既是侦探  也是考古学家
Are you an archaeologist as well as a detective?
好吧  在绕来绕去飘忽扭曲时间暴风雪中降落
Okay, landing a plane in a timey wimey blizzard.
我可以勉强办到  但是
I could push through, but,
如果我出了哪怕一纳秒偏差
if I'm out by a nanosecond,
引擎就会故障  而我会炸碎整个地球
the engines will phase and I'll shatter the planet.
-我需要着陆灯  -着陆灯
- I need landing lights. - Landing lights?
对  我需要一个能锁定的信号
Yes, I need a signal to lock on to.
她怎么说的来着  什么朝早期
What did she say, early what dynasty?
秦朝早期  如你所说
Early Chin, just as you say.
你看来见多识广啊
You're very well-informed.
而你非常害怕
And you're very afraid.
一扇门上那么多锁
That's an awful lot of locks for one door.
瑞雯  我眼里自动翻译了
River, I'm translating.
这是塔迪斯的礼物  会保留一段时间
It's a gift of the TARDIS. It hangs around.
这个人
This one.
扔去不舒服的地方
Put him somewhere uncomfortable.
去陪着小孩吗  先生
With the babies, sir?
对  有何不可  把他给那些小孩
Yes. Why not? Give him to the babies.
灯坏了
The lights are out.
拿上这个  你能撑更久
You'll last longer with these.
你帮我干什么
What do you care?
那样更好玩
It's funnier.
谁
Hello?
中国  公元前221年
你好
Ah, hello. Yes.
皇上御批的特别许可
Special permission from the emperor.
哎呀妈呀
你好啊亲爱的
Hello, sweetie.
我看看
Let's see...
有收集癖的犯罪头目
crime boss with a collecting fetish.
不管你有什么不得见人的东西
Whatever you don't want anyone else to see
肯定都是你的最爱
has got to be your favorite.
甚至可能是  你的女友
Or, possibly, your girlfriend.
看来就是女友了
So, girlfriend, then.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你也知道
Oh, you know,
给男人发短信
texting a boy.
哎呀妈呀
信号已锁定
着陆灯来了
Landing lights.
有信号了
We have a signal.
锁定中
Locking on.
这些东西到处都是
These things are all over,
但人们似乎视而不见
but people don't seem to notice.
你看着时它们从来不动
It never moves while you're looking.
我知道他们是怎么回事
Oh, I know how they work.
我也清楚你是知道的
So I understand.
梅乐蒂·梅隆
Melody Malone,
调查天使的侦探
the detective who investigates Angels.
损伤严重
Badly damaged.
我想知道
I wanted to know
它能否感到痛苦
if it could feel pain.
你应该知道它一旦尖叫
You realize it's screaming?
其它的也会听见
The others can hear.
所以你才需要那么多锁
Is that why you need all the locks?
你要把这种怪物的一切都告诉我
You're going to tell me all about these creatures.
而且你要快点说
And you're going to do it quickly.
谁在那边
Hello, is someone there?
拜托
Come on!
天使是狩猎者
The Angels are predators.
非常危险  你想要它们做什么
They're deadly. What do you want with them?
我是个收藏家
I'm a collector.
收藏家怎么能拒绝这些呢
What collector could resist these?
我只是人类
I'm only human.
他们也是这么想的
That's exactly what they're thinking.
什么  怎么回事
What's that? What's happening?
发生地震了吗
Is it an earthquake?
怎么回事
What is it?!
好你个坏小子
Oh, you bad boy.
当心把纽约烧平了
You could burn New York.
到底是什么意思
What does that mean?!
意思就是  格雷尔先生
It means, Mr. Grayle,
你且等着我丈夫回家吧
just you wait 'til my husband gets home.
快点
Come on.
稍等  最后整理一下仪容仪表
Just a moment. Final checks.
你什么时候整理过
Since when?
罗伊
Rory?
Rory!
罗伊
Rory?!
抱歉来晚了  亲爱的
Sorry I'm late, honey.
路况太差
Traffic was hell.
昏过去了
Shock.
他不会有事的
He'll be fine.
等我脱身  他就有事了
Not if I can get loose.
所以我们现在到哪了  宋博士
So where are we now, Dr. Song?
监狱生活可好
How's prison?
我都被赦免不知道多少年了
Oh, I was pardoned ages ago.
而且现在你该叫我宋教授
And it's "Professor" Song, to you.
赦免
Pardoned?
原来我杀掉的人
Turns out the person I killed
从一开始就不存在
never existed, in the first place.
显然他没有任何记录可查
Apparently, there's no record of him.
简直就好像有人四处删除自己的痕迹
It's almost as if someone's gone around, deleting himself
从全宇宙的数据库中消失
from every database in the universe.
是你说我太自大了
Mmm, you said I'd got too big.
现在没人听说过你
And, now, no one's ever heard of you.
你以前不是个大人物吗
Didn't you used to be somebody?
你以前不是杀了博士的女人吗
Weren't you the woman who killed the Doctor?
哪个博士
Doctor who?
她握你握得非常紧
She's holding you very tight.
至少她还没把我送回过去
At least she didn't send me back in time.
我看她没那么强壮
I doubt she's strong enough.
可是我需要我的手包
Well, I need a handbag.
所以你要选哪个
So which is it going to be,
掰断她的手腕  还是我的
are you going to break my wrist or hers?
别啊
Oh, no.
真的吗
Really?
你为什么非得弄断我的
Why do you have to break mine?
因为艾米在书里看到过
Because Amy read it in a book
而我现在没有选择
and, now, I have no choice.
看见了吗
You see?
什么书
Well, what book?
你的书
Your book.
而你现在还没写  所以我们不能看
Which you haven't written yet, so we can't read!
梅乐蒂·梅隆
这样啊  我不喜欢这个封面
I see. I don't like the cover much.
但如果是瑞雯要写这本书
But if River's going to write that book,
那她就能用上了  对不对
she'd make it useful, yeah?
我确实试过了
Well, I'll certainly try.
但我们不能提前读  太危险了
But we can't read ahead. It's too dangerous.
我知道  但肯定有什么我们能看的东西
I know, but there must be something we can look at.
什么  一整页直白的提示
What, a page of handy hints,
还是无剧透预览
previews, spoilerfree?
章节标题
Chapter titles.
濒死神探
天使占领曼哈顿
迷失纽约
接受委托
雕像公园之夜
石像鬼
瘦削男
尤利乌斯·格雷尔
呼叫博士
地下室的罗马人
死亡冬季码头
他在地下室
He's in the cellar.
给我
Gimme.
博士
Doctor?
博士  怎么了
Doctor, what is it?
出什么问题了  告诉我
What's wrong? Tell me.
博士
Doctor.
博士  怎么了  告诉我
Doctor, what is it? Tell me.
艾米莉亚的永别
好吧  我认得那个表情
Okay, I know that face.
冷静
Calm down!
-不  -博士  告诉我
- No! - Talk to me! Doctor!
不  你快把手腕挣出来
No! You get your wrist out.
把手腕挣出来  不要弄断
You get your wrist out without breaking it.
-怎么做  -我不知道  反正快点
- How? - I don't know. Just do it!
改变未来
Change the future!
罗伊
Rory?
不要
No!
它们是天使
They're Angels!
幼儿天使
Baby Angels.
罗伊被他们抓走了吗
Did they get Rory?
他在哪  被它们劫走了吗
Where is he? Did they take him?
我看是
Yes, I think so, yes.
冬季码头
所以这就是未来吗
So is this what's going to happen?
我们只要不停地回到过去救他
We just keep chasing him back in time
然后它们就把他送到更远的过去
and they keep pulling him further back.
他没有回到过去  我发现了一处扭曲
He isn't back in time. I'm reading a displacement,
但没发现时空标记
but there are no temporal markers.
他只是被空间移动了  而不是时间
He's been moved in space, not in time,
而且离这里不远
and it's not that far from here,
从数据来看的话
by the look of it.
你挣出来了
You got out.
所以他在哪
So where is he?
拜托  拜托  他到底在哪
Well, come on, come on, come on, where is he?!
要是这么好找的话我就让你来找了
If it was that easy, I'd get you to do it.
但是你是怎么把手腕挣脱出来
How did you get your wrist out
却没弄断手腕的
without breaking it?
你要求  我照办  有问题吗
You asked. I did. Problem?
你改变了未来
You just changed the future!
这就叫婚姻  亲爱的
It's called "Marriage," Honey.
安静点  我这忙着呢
Now, hush. I'm working.
她厉害吧
She's good, huh?
你没发现吗  她真的厉害
Have you noticed? Really, really good.
有了  不管在哪  都离这里只有几个街区
Ah, wherever it is, it's within a few blocks.
正门外有辆车  我们偷走吧
There's a car out front. Shall we steal it?
带我去看
Show me!
好了  当两个单元的数据都变成零了
Okay, when all those numbers on both units go to zero,
我们就锁定位置了  明白了吗
that's when we've got a lock, okay?
这样就能找到罗伊了
That's how we find Rory.
明白
Got it.
你为什么骗我
Why did you lie to me?
当一个人爱上永生不老的神
When one's in love with an ageless God
而这个神偏偏又保持着12岁的面容
who insists on the face of a 12-year-old,
人就会尽力掩藏受到的伤害
one does one's best to hide the damage.
肯定很疼
It must hurt.
给我
Come here.
对
Yes.
手腕的伤也很严重
The wrist is pretty bad, too.
不  不行
No. No.
不  住手  快停下
No, stop that. Stop that!
停下
Stop it!
好了
There you are.
好些了吗
How's that?
好吧
Well,
我们就来看看吧
let's see, shall we?
在这里浪费重生能量太蠢了
That was a stupid waste of regeneration energy.
你做一个多愁善感的白痴没有任何好处
Nothing is gained by you being a sentimental idiot!
瑞雯
River!
不  你太让我丢人了
No! You embarrass me!
瑞雯
River!
我告诉你
Tell you what...
把你的头脑专注在科学上
stick to the science part.
好了  你为什么撒谎
Okay, why did you lie?
不能让他看到后果
Never let him see the damage.
而且永远  永远
And never, ever,
也不能让他看着你变老
let him see you age.
他不喜欢结束
He doesn't like endings.
冬季码头
原来在这里
There you are.
找到了
Got it!
他在一个叫冬季码头的地方
He's in a place called Winter Quay.
就是这辆车吧  我们走
The car, yes? Let's go.
他们为什么要把他送到这里
Why would they send him here?
为什么不直接把他送回过去
Why not zap him back in time,
就像往常那样
like they normally do?
等知道了这地方是什么地方  就清楚了
We'll know that when we know what this place is.
冬季码头
Winter Quay.
罗伊
Rory.
他就在附近了
He's close.
罗伊
Rory!
艾米
Amy.
博士
Doctor.
你看
Look at this.
它为什么在笑
Why is it smiling?
罗·威廉姆斯
艾米  罗伊
Amy. Rory!
快出来  什么都别看
Get out of here. Don't look at anything.
什么都别碰
Don't touch anything.
那是谁
Who's that?
艾米
Amy!
艾米  求你了
Amy, please.
艾米
Amy.
求你了
Please.
罗伊
Rory.
他就是你
He's you.
艾米
Amy.
拜托谁给我解释一下  到底是怎么回事
Someone, please, tell me what is going on.
抱歉了罗伊
I'm sorry, Rory,
但你刚刚死了
but you just died.
死亡冬季码头
这个地方被天使完全监视
This place is policed by Angels.
每次你试图逃走
Every time you try to escape,
你就会被送回过去
you get zapped back in time.
所以天使控制了这个地方
So this place belongs to the Angels?
是它们建造的吗
They built it?
把人送回过去会创造时间能量
Displacing someone back in time creates time energy,
而天使就是以那种能量为食
and that is what the Angels feed on.
但通常只是一次性作案
But, normally, it's a one-off,
肇完事就逃逸
a hit-and-run.
如果它们能把受害者关起来
If they could keep hold of their victims,
反复吞食他们的时间能量
feed off their time energy over and over again...
这里就是个农场
This place is a farm,
是能量种植场
a battery farm.
纽约有多少天使
How many Angels in New York?
好像全城的雕像都被它们取代了
It's like they've taken over every statue in the city.
没错  天使占领曼哈顿因为它们可以
Yeah, the Angels take Manhattan because they can.
因为他们找到了前所未有的食物来源
Because they've never had a food source like this one,
一座不夜城
the city that never sleeps.
那是什么
What was that?
我不知道
I don't know.
但我认为是冲你来的
But I think they're coming for you.
这是什么意思
What does that mean?
我最后会怎么样
What is going to happen to me?
我到底会怎样
What is physically going to happen?
天使会来抓走你
The Angels will come for you.
他们把你传送回三四十年前的同一个地方
They'll zap you back in time, to this very spot, 30 40 years ago,
然后你的余生会在那个房间里度过
and you will live out the rest of your life in that room,
直到你死在那张床上
until you die in that bed.
艾米会在吗
And will Amy be there?
不在
No.
你怎么知道
How do you know?
因为他再次看到你时  是那么高兴
Because he was so pleased to see you again.
好吧  它们现在还没抓走我
Okay. Well, they haven't taken me yet.
如果我跑掉呢
What if I just run?
如果我离开这个地方呢
What if I just get the hell out of here?
这样刚才的一切从未发生
Then that never happens.
已经发生了  罗伊
It's already happened, Rory.
你刚刚目睹了你自己的未来
You've just witnessed your own future.
-博士他说得对  -不  他错了
- Doctor, he's right. - No, he isn't.
如果罗伊逃出去了  就会制造一个悖论
If Rory got out, it would create a paradox,
那到底是什么
What is that?
这里是天使的食物来源
This is the Angels' food source.
悖论会污染整个食物源
The paradox poisons the well.
会把它们全部杀死
It could kill them all.
那么这整个地方的事就从未发生过
This whole place would literally unhappen.
但那几乎不可能
It would be almost impossible.
我就喜欢"几乎"两个字
Loving the "Almost".
但是制造一个那样的悖论
But to create a paradox like that
需要几乎无法想象的巨大能量
takes almost unimaginable power.
我们手里有什么  告诉我
What have we got? Eh? Tell me.
说啊  有什么
Come on, what?
我不会让它们夺走他的
I won't let them take him.
我们就有这么大的决心
That's what we got.
不管是什么东西
Whatever that thing is,
都越来越近了
it's getting closer.
罗伊
Rory,
就算你逃出来了
even if you got out,
你的余生也还是要不停地逃跑
you'd have to keep running for the rest of your life.
它们会永远不停地追杀你
They would be chasing you forever.
那我们赶紧开始吧
Well, then, better get started.
老公  快跑
Husband, run!
瑞雯  我不确定这个办法能行
River, I'm not sure this can work.
老公  闭嘴
Husband, shut up.
-去楼上  -向上有什么好处
- Up! - What good's up?
总比向下走好
Better than down.
我不能一直这么做
I can't keep doing this.
-有办法吗  -有  和往常一样
Any ideas? Yeah, the usual.
跑
Run.
好吧  逃生通道
Uh, okay, fire escape.
冬季码头
我一直想去自由女神像看看
I always wanted to visit the Statue of Liberty.
看来她等不及我了
I guess she got impatient.
什么  怎么了  你干什么
What? What is it? What?
你就一直盯着
Just keep your eyes on that!
有下去的路吗
Is there a way down?
这个  没有
Uh...no.
但确实有一条路出去
But there's a way out.
你要干什么
What are you doing?
罗伊  你干什么
Rory, what are you doing?
罗伊
Rory.
下来  你会死的
Stop it! You'll die.
对  死两次
Yeah, twice.
同一天晚上  在同一幢大楼里
In the same building on the same night.
谁还能做到
Who else could do that?
下来吧  求你了
Just come down, please.
这才是正确的做法
This is the right thing to do.
这样会有用的  如果我这回死了
This will work. If I die now,
悖论就产生了  对不对
it's a paradox, right?
悖论会杀死天使的
The paradox will kill the Angels.
难道我错了吗
Tell me I'm wrong.
说啊  求你说我错了  因为我很害怕
Go on, please, because I am really scared.
很好
Great.
这一次  你终于没办法了
The one time you can't manage it.
我的天
Oh, God.
艾米
Amy.
我需要一点小小的帮助
I'm going to need a little help here.
你别闹了
Just stop it!
不是  你仔细想想
No, just think it through.
这样能行  这样能杀死天使
This will work. This will kill the Angels.
-但也会杀死你  -会吗  瑞雯说过
- It will kill you, too. - Will it?! River said that
这个大楼会从时间中抹除  从没存在过
this place would be erased from time, never exist.
既然大楼从未存在  那我跳的是什么
If this place never existed, what did I fall off?
你以为你就会这么死而复生吗
You think you'll just come back to life?
-我哪次不是呢  -罗伊
- When don't I? - Rory!
而且再说了  否则还有什么办法
And, anyway, what else is there?
在楼下活活老死  永远见不到你
Dying of old age downstairs, never seeing you again.
艾米  求你了
Amy, please.
如果你真的爱我
If you love me,
那就相信我  推我一把
then trust me and push.
-我做不到  -你必须做到
- I can't. - You have to!
那你能吗
Could you?
如果换了是我  你忍心推吗
If it was me, could you do it?
为了救你
To save you,
我什么都能做
I could do anything.
那就证明给我看
Prove it.
不行  我不能拖累你
No, I can't take you, too.
你说我们会死而复生的
You said we'd come back to life.
到了实践检验一下的时候了
"Money where your mouth is" time.
-艾米  -闭嘴
- Amy! - Shut. Up.
我们一起
Together.
否则就都不跳
Or not at all.
你们在干什么
What the hell are you doing?!
改变未来
Changing the future.
这就是婚姻
It's called "Marriage."
艾米
Amy!
博士
Doctor!
发生什么了
What's happening?!
悖论
The paradox,
起作用了
it's working.
悖论起作用了
The paradox is working!
我们在哪
Where are we?
回到了起点
Back where we started!
你们让时间线崩溃了  悖论起作用了
You collapsed the timeline. The paradox worked.
我们都回到了该来的地方
We all pinged back where we belong.
什么  就该来墓园吗
What, in a graveyard?
上次也是这样  为什么总是这里
This happened last time. Why always here?
有关系吗  我们运气好
Does it matter? We got lucky!
我们本来可能把纽约炸到外太空的
We could've blown New York off the planet.
我永远也不能开着塔迪斯回去了
I can't ever take the TARDIS back there.
时间线太乱了
The timelines are too scrambled.
我差点就失去你们两个了
Oh, I could've lost you both.
再也不要这样做了
Don't ever do that again.
我们做什么了
What did we do?
我们想出了办法  解决了问题
We fixed it. We solved the problem.
我是在说我自己
I was talking to myself.
需要重新刷一次漆了
It could do with a repaint.
我一直很忙
I've been busy.
顶上的灯泡需要换吗
Does the bulb on top need changing?
刚刚换过
Just changed it.
那么
So,
罗伊和艾米
Rory and Amy, then.
我知道  我知道
Yes, I know. I know.
我就是说  整天在塔迪斯上晃
I'm just saying, they're going to get terribly bored,
他们会无聊死的
hanging round here all day.
博士
Doctor.
下一次就不能简单地去个酒吧吗
Next time, can we just go to the pub?
我现在就想去酒吧
I want to go to the pub right now.
那里有电子游戏吗  我就喜欢电子游戏
Are there videogames there? I love videogames.
好了  合家出游
Right, family outing, then.
艾米  来看看
Amy! Come see this.
怎么了
What?
这里的这个墓碑
There's a gravestone here
深切缅怀
罗伊·亚瑟·威廉姆斯
上面的人名字和我一样
for someone with the same name as me.
什么
What?
博士
Doctor!
那个东西是从哪出来的
Where the hell did that come from?
是个幸存者  非常虚弱
It's a survivor. Very weak.
但一定要一直盯着它
But keep your eyes on it.
罗伊在哪
Where's Rory?
深切缅怀
罗伊·亚瑟·威廉姆斯  享年82岁
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
艾米莉亚
Amelia.
我非常  非常抱歉
I'm so, so sorry.
不
No.
不对  我们可以去找他  让他回到塔迪斯
No, we can just go and get him in the TARDIS.
再来一次悖论
One more paradox.
那样就会撕碎纽约  而且我
Would rip New York apart and I...
不  那不是真的  我不相信你
No, that's not true. I don't believe you.
母亲  是真的
Mother, it's true.
艾米  你要做什么
Amy? What are you doing?
罗伊的墓碑
That gravestone, Rory's,
上面的空间足够写两个人的名字  对吗
there's room for one more name, isn't there?
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
离天使远点  回塔迪斯上去
Back away from the Angel. Come back to the TARDIS!
我们再想办法
We'll figure something out!
天使会把我送到和他相同的时间  对不对
The Angel, would it send me back to the same time, to him?
我不知道  没人知道
I don't know. Nobody knows.
但这是我最大的机会了  对吗
But it's my best shot, yeah?
不
No!
博士  闭嘴  没错  你说得对
Doctor, shut up! Yes, yes, it is!
-艾米  -那好  我只要眨眼就行了  对不对
- Amy... - Well, then, I just have to blink, right?
不要
No!
没事的  我知道不会有事的
It'll be fine. I know it will.
我会和他在一起  我应该和他在一起
I'll... I'll be with him, like I should be.
我和罗伊  永远在一起
Me and Rory, together.
梅乐蒂
Melody.
停下  你们都停下
Stop it! Just... just stop it!
你照顾好他
You look after him.
你一定要乖乖的
And you be a good girl
照顾好他
and you look after him.
你这是制造一个时间定点
You are creating a fixed time.
我永远也不能再见到你了
I will never be able to see you again.
没事的  我还有他
I'll be fine. I'll be with him.
艾米  求求你
Amy, please.
求你
Just...
回到塔迪斯里
Come back into the TARDIS.
来吧  庞德  我求你了
Come on, Pond, please.
邋遢男
Raggedy man,
永别了
goodbye.
深切缅怀
罗伊·亚瑟·威廉姆斯  享年82岁
及爱妻
艾米莉亚·威廉姆斯  享年87岁
不
No!
瑞雯
River.
他们是你的父母
They were your parents.
对不起
Sorry.
我根本没想到
I didn't even think.
没关系
It doesn't matter.
当然有关系
Of course it matters.
重要的是
What matters is this:
博士
Doctor,
千万不要一个人旅行
don't travel alone.
那你跟我一起吧
Travel with me, then.
无论何时何地  我都陪着你
Whenever and wherever you want.
但不会一直待着
But not all the time.
一台塔迪斯上有一个疯子就够了  你说呢
One pyschopath per TARDIS, don't you think?
好吧
Okay,
我注定要写的这本书
this book I've got to write,
《梅乐蒂·梅隆》
Melody Malone.
想必是我寄给艾米  让她帮我出版吧
I presume I send it to Amy to get it published?
对  是
Yes. Yes.
那我让她写一篇后记
I'll tell her to write an afterword.
为了你
For you.
也许你会听她的劝
Maybe you'll listen to her.
最后一页
The last page.
后记  艾米莉亚·威廉姆斯
Afterword, by Amelia Williams.
你好啊老友
Hello, old friend.
你和我  终于在这最后一页相遇了
And here we are, you and me, on the last page.
你读到这段话的时候
By the time you read these words,
罗伊和我应该已经离开好久了
Rory and I will be long gone.
告诉你一下  我们生活得很安宁  很幸福
So know that we lived well and were very happy.
最重要的是
And, above all else,
你要知道  我们永远爱你
know that we will love you always.
不过有时我确实会担心你
Sometimes I do worry about you, though.
我以为我们走之后
I think, once we're gone,
你可能一段时间内都不会回到这里
you won't be coming back here for a while
你会一个人旅行
and you might be alone,
但你不能一个人
which you should never be.
不要独自旅行  博士
Don't be alone, Doctor.
而且再为我做一件事
And do one more thing for me.
后院里有一个等待着的小女孩
There's a little girl waiting in a garden.
她会等好久好久
She's going to wait a long while,
所以她会需要很多希望
so she's going to need a lot of hope.
去找她  给她讲个故事
Go to her. Tell her a story.
告诉她  只要她耐心一点
Tell her that, if she's patient,
那些她永远难忘的日子必将到来
the days are coming that she'll never forget.
S06E03
告诉她  她会见识大海高山  会和海盗战斗
Tell her she'll go to sea and fight pirates.
她会爱上一个人
She'll fall in love with a man
这个人守护了她两千年
who'll wait 2,000 years to keep her safe,
S05E12-13
S05E10
告诉她  她会给予最伟大的画家生活的希望
tell her she'll give hope to the greatest painter who ever lived
而且还会拯救一只外太空鲸鱼
and save a whale in outer space.
S05E02
告诉她
Tell her
这就是艾米莉亚·庞德的故事
this is the story of Amelia Pond...
这就是故事的结局
And this is how it ends.
■
新版DW从第一集起一直沿用的时空漩涡片头
将从下集2012圣诞特辑起进行更换
而十一任博士的塔迪斯控制室也将第一次进行大规模改造
根据本集中小说《梅乐蒂·梅隆》短暂闪现的内文内容
剧组所用的道具书其实是美国硬汉侦探小说作家达谢尔·哈梅特
于1933年出版的小说《瘦子》
2012年圣诞特辑
神秘博士  精彩继续